<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Yorke against popish transubstantiation, and their communion vnder one kinde, the first Sunday in Lent, Ann. Dom. 1607. By Thomas Dodson, Maister of artes.</title>
            <author>Dodson, Thomas, Master of Arts.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20588</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852697</idno>
  <idno type="VID">18034</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240885780</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 6990</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117484</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99852697e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18034)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1234:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Yorke against popish transubstantiation, and their communion vnder one kinde, the first Sunday in Lent, Ann. Dom. 1607. By Thomas Dodson, Maister of artes.</title>
                  <author>Dodson, Thomas, Master of Arts.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. L[ownes] for Mathew Lownes, and are to be sould at his shioppe in Paules Churchyard, at the signe of the Bishoppes head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church of Yorke, <hi>against Popish Transubstantiation,</hi> and their Communion vnder one kinde, the first Sunday in Lent, Ann. Dom. 1607.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THOMAS DODSON, <hi>Maister of Artes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IEREMIE, 6. vers. 16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus saith the Lord; Stand in the wayes and behold, and aske for the olde way, which is the good way and walke therein, and yee shall finde rest for your soules: but they sayde, Wee will not walke therein.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Imp<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nted at London by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Mathew Lown<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be sould at his Shoppe in Paules Churchyard, at the signe of the Bishoppes head. 160<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND AND</hi> VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Gentlewoman, Mistresse <hi>CATHERINE FOVVBERIE</hi> Widdowe, his <hi>verie louing Mother in Law, health and true happinesse in this life, and in the life to come, through Iesus Christ.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I could be resolued (Right Christian, and most deare Mother) to handle this Text, I was driuen into a doubtfull meditation, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of a double consideration. For considering that I was to speake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great men, in a great Auditorie: I doubted, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it should bee more expedient, to teach from this Text <hi>non-communicants</hi> to forsake their former er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and to renounce their superstitious vanities; or to inuite from another Text all in generall to a Lents Potation. Whereof thus musing and meditating, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came in the end resolued, to make choice of this Text ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not onely in regard that the feast of Easter draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neere: but in respect especially, that some euen <hi>ex
<pb facs="tcp:18034:3"/> meis intimis,</hi> otherwise vertuously inclined, are not rightly resolued how to eate the Lords Bread at the Lords Table, and to drink of his Cup. Concerning whose wilfull blindnes, and blind wilfulnes, sparing to speake I sigh to see, and rew to knowe, what I fully knowe: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I protest before God, calling in this Sermon both the holie Scriptures, and holy Fathers to witnesse, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is no truth, or else that the points of Poperie (which <hi>non-communicants,</hi> like halting hypocrites, now embrace) are most false. Which rude Sermon and simple, but such as it is, vpon the assurance of your knowne courtesie, and to the end especially that a scant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heereby of that religion, which once (O happie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersiō!) you professed, may be taken; I now offer in way of thankefulnesse for vndeserued kindnesses, and in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of great gratitude due vnto your Worship. Accept therefore (right vertuous &amp; euer kind Mother) I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseech you this poore present, and present exercise, as a poore sparke of great good will: wherein if any good thing be found, giue God (I pray you) the glorie; if any fault, impute it vnto me: and pray vnto God, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I neuer speake, or else speake to his glorie. Thus beseeching the God of all grace, the Author, and giuer of all good gifts, to grant vnto your Worship increase of spirituall graces, and continuance of bodily health, with wealth and welfare in this life present and in the life to come euerlasting blessednesse; I leaue you, and your meditation vpon this Sermon, to the guidance &amp; gratious assistance of the Almightie whom I beseech so to blesse you in reading, as that being throughly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued, how to receiue Christs holy Mysteries, you may stedfastly stand in the right profession of Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb facs="tcp:18034:3"/> and euer wish the prosperitie of them that loue it, and labour for it: which the Lord in mercie grant vnto euerie Christian subiect.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Goodmaudam</hi> in <hi>Yorkeshire,</hi>
                  <date>this last of March, 1608.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By him that is vnworthie of your<lb/> motherly fauour, yet deuoted<lb/> to honour you,</hi>
                  <lb/> Thomas Dodson.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, I haue here set down (so neere as I could remember) whatsoeuer was spoken in deliuering this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: yea, and more matter then the time suffered; but not more then was purposed to bee vttered. For being gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced beyond expectation with the gratious presence of the most reuerend Father in God the Lord Archb. of <hi>Yorke</hi> his Grace, after his paines taken according to godlinesse else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Citie; I was in regard thereof rather contented abruptly to end, then to be troublesome: whereupon partly, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to profit such abroad as hauing eares to heare, and soules to saue, do want instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I became resolued to penne this my then exercise, and to put it into print. Now iudge not rashly (gentle Reader) I most hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily desire thee, in that I being the vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of many hundreths, and the vnablest of
<pb facs="tcp:18034:4"/> many thousands, haue taken vpon me to set forth, and to publish any thing, to the open light and sight of the world: for wee knowe, that the poore Widdowes mite (where God is made Vmpire) shall not bee refused. And the Lord the searcher of the harts and reines, knoweth my purpose and affection in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and publishing this matter: wherein, if any thing be amisse (my amisse once discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the pen of the learned) <hi>Peccaui</hi> shal be my Plea: for <hi>haereticū me esse nolo.</hi> Thus I leaue thee, committing this my simple labour vnto the blessing of Gods holy spirit: who grant vs a right vnderstanding heart, with a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble friendly Iudgement in all things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18034:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MATH. 26. 26, 27.</bibl>
               <q>Iesus tooke the bread, and when hee had blessed, hee brake it, and gaue it to the Disciples, and said, Take, eate, this is my Bodie. Also hee tooke the Cuppe, and when he had giuen thankes, hee gaue it to them, saying, Drinke ye all of it, &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not mine intent (most Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father, Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Right Worshipfull, and in the Lord beloued) to speake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at this time cōcerning the Author of this Sacrament of the Bodie &amp; Bloud of Christ, concerning the time when it was ordained, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ende why it was ordained, or concerning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other circumstāces hereunto belonging; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so farre forth, as the controuersie betweene vs and the Papistes shall leade mee. Which controuersie and dissention may not bee passed ouer without dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18034:6"/> examination, and due consideration, considering that our aduersaries in their grosse and absurd opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, rent with their teeth him that made them, and so dishonour him, whome they ought to honour. Now, all the reason that they build vpon, is but the wordes onely of the Institution. Christ saide, <hi>This is my bodie: Ergo</hi> say they, it is his Bodie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I might answere, that by like argument they may prooue as well that Christ is a Doore; because hee sayth <hi>I am that doore:</hi> or that hee is a naturall Vine; because hee sayth, <hi>I am that true Vine.</hi> But aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering <note place="margin">Iohn, 10, 9. &amp; 15. 1.</note> I do saie with Saint <hi>Hierome, That the Gospell standeth not in the bare wordes of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures but in the meaning.</hi> As also aunswering, I do say with Saint <hi>Augustine, that there is nothing spoken obscurely in one place of Scripture, which is not made plaine and verie cleare in some other:</hi> And that therefore wee may not (like men factious rather then religious) bring our owne senses to the reading of the Scriptures; but wee are to take the sense that the Scripture giueth, by conferring one Scripture with another: for otherwise, to take a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue speech properly and according to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, destroyeth the soule. Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in his Booke <hi>De doctrina Christiana,</hi> giueth diuerse lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Lessons, whereby to knowe a figuratiue speech; one of which lessons is this: <hi>If the Scripture see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to cōmand a wicked thing &amp; vngodly, or to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid a thing that charitie requireth, then knowe</hi> (sayth hee) <hi>that the speach is figuratiue.</hi> According to which rule, and direction, Christ his wordes in the Institution of this Sacrament are to bee vnderstood
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18034:6"/> figuratiuely: for, Christ commaunding at his last Supper to eate his Bodie and to drinke his Bloude, seemed to commaund in sound of wordes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience and a wicked thing. Yea, to say that the breade is Christes Bodie in proper speach and according to the letter, is horrible blasphemie: for if bread in proper speach bee the flesh of Christ, then bread is also the seed of <hi>Dauid:</hi> then bread was fastened to the Crosse for our sinnes: then breade <note place="margin">Blush at this yee Papistes.</note> was buried, rose the thirde day from death, and now sitteth in heauen at the right hand of GOD the Father: yea, if bread be Christ, then is bread the Son of God, and second person in the sacred Trinity. Nay, no question if bread bee truely and properly Christ according to a literall and carnall construction: then (besides these monstrous impieties, which cannot be auoyded) it must needes ensue, that really wee eate Christes flesh in the sacrament with our mouthes, &amp; actually drinke his bloud with our lippes; which is a thing hainous and horrible in Christian religion &amp; behauiour: yea, as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> auoucheth, <hi>It is more horrible to eat mans flesh thē to kil it, and to drink mans bloud thē to shed it.</hi> But some peraduenture obiecting will say, that Christ said, <hi>My flesh is meate indeed, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note>
               <hi>my bloud is drink indeed.</hi> Wherunto in answering, it behoueth to make a difference between the bodie of Christ and the Sacrament of his body, least wee bee deceiued, and take one for another. And therefore <note place="margin">Note this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. Tra. 26. In Ioh.</note> I do say with Saint <hi>Augustine, that the Sacrament (of Christs body) is receiued of some vnto life, and of some vnto destruction: but the thing it selfe (that is, the flesh of Christ) whereof this is a Sacrament, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18034:7"/> receiued of all men vnto life, and of no man to destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> yea, his flesh is so truely meate, and his blood is so truely drinke, as that whosoeuer doubteth of this wee hold him accursed: but, for what part of man (soule, or body) this meat was prouided, in this stāds the difference betweene vs and the Papistes. They say, for the body, no lesse then for the soule: wee say for the soule, and not for the body: Now to make this point plaine on our side, and so to ende this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie; if their mouthes bee not farre out of taste, I will plainely proue by testimonies of the holie Scriptures, as also of the holy ancient Fathers, that Christ his flesh and bloud is sustenance not for the body, but onely for the soule. <hi>Doe you not knowe</hi> (sayth Christ) <hi>that whatsoeuer thing from without</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 7.</note>
               <hi>entreth into a man, cānot defile him: because it entreth not into his hart, but into the bellie.</hi> Whereby it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euen in the iudgement of our Sauiour, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can enter both the heart and the bellie: but the flesh of Christ entreth into the heart: <hi>Ergo,</hi> not into the bellie. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> likewise sayeth, <hi>Meates</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note>
               <hi>are ordained for the bellie, and the belly for meates; but God will destroy both it, and them:</hi> but the body of Christ God will not destroy: it is therefore no meate for the belly. To bee short, that which doth either defile or sanctifie, is not meat for the belly: for <hi>meates do not commend vs vnto God,</hi> 1. Cor. 8. 8. But <hi>Christ with his bloud doth sanctifie,</hi> Heb. 13, 12. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Christ his flesh and bloud is not meate for the belly.</p>
            <p>Other arguments to this effect, and to set foorth the truth hereof, I could vse many: but let these and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18034:7"/> all other proofes bee voyde, if the learned auncient Fathers do not hereunto subscribe, and euen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the verie same point. Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> sayth, <hi>Christ is the Bread, which feedeth not the bodie, but</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chrysost. In Mat. 9.</note>
               <hi>the soule, and filleth not the bellie, but the minde.</hi> Ambrose, <hi>Hee is not bodilie, but ghostly meate.</hi> Augustine, <hi>It is not lawfull to deuoure Christ with teeth. Prepare not your Iawes, but your heartes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de cons. Dist. 2. Cypr. de. Coena Dom.</note> And Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> sayth, <hi>The bodie of Christ is</hi> cibus mentis, non ventris, <hi>is meate for the minde, not for the bellie:</hi> not for the teeth to chewe, but for the soule to beleeue. The Testimonie of all which good and lawfull witnesses, is sufficient to remoue vs from the corporall eating of Christs flesh with teeth and iawes. Indeede touching the visible part of this Sacrament, as the bread and wine, which is seene with eyes, felt with hands, and brused with teeth, of that there is no doubt, but it entereth our mouthes and resteth in our bowels: but to say, that the naturall flesh of Christ entereth the mouth, or passeth downe the throat, or lodgeth in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, is a position (as you haue heard) altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repugnant both to the holie Scriptures, and holy Fathers. But our aduersaries the Papistes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to presse the truth, though they cannot oppresse it, will peraduenture obiect and say, Christ is Almightie and can do all thinges; therefore being <note place="margin">A possibili ad esse, non valet consequentia.</note> able to turne breade into his bodie at his last Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, hee did it. Whereunto I might replie, that GOD was able to make vs Swine, Sheepe, Oxen, Horses, Frogges, Dogges, &amp;c. yet hee hath not done so: But aunswering, I do say, that though God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18034:8"/> is able to do whatsoeuer he wil, yet he wil do none of those thinges that bee not in him of their owne nature. Sith then, that GOD is true of his owne nature, hee canne doe nothing, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his worde: not because that hee is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do it, but because his Power doth neuer ouertwharte and crosse his Will. Indeede hee is Almightie in working his will: but not in chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his nature; for that which hee will not, that hee doth not: and therefore to imagine what wee list, and then to father our falshoodes on Christes Almightie power, is errour, impietie, yea, insolent blasphemie. But passing ouer this Popish argument from <hi>can</hi> to <hi>will,</hi> whereupon no argument followeth: I will now plainely proue by the worde of trueth, and testimonie also of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, that the bread in the Sacrament is not the substance, but a signe of Christes bodie: and that the nature of it remaineth (howsoeuer the popish sort iangle) after the wordes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secration. Christ at his last Supper tooke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but breade, hee brake nothing but breade, hee gaue into the handes of his Disciples, to eate, nothing but breade, and <hi>(as appeareth by my Text)</hi> hee called nothing his body, but euen the same breade, which hee had taken, which he had broken, and which hee gaue vnto them. Now, in thus calling the breade his bodie, it was in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie and figure, not in nature and substance: and therefore it is but as if hee had sayde, This breade which I haue in my handes is a signe of my body which shortly after shall bee crucified, and deliuered
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18034:8"/> vnto death for your saluation. To which effect, after this manner thus speaketh Saint <hi>Cyprian: Dedit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. de vncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Chrisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note>
               <hi>noster in mensa, in qua vltimum cum Apostolis participauit conuiuium, &amp;c.</hi> Our Lord at the Table, whereat he receiued his last Supper with his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, gaue with his owne hands bread and wine: but vpon the Crosse, he gaue his own body to be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the hands of the souldiers. Where hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a difference betweene that which Christ gaue vpon the Crosse, and that which hee gaue at the Table: at the Table hee gaue bread and wine; vpon the Crosse, hee gaue his bodie and bloud. Likewise else where, hee calleth the bread after consecration, <hi>Panem ex multorum granorum adunatione congestum.</hi> Bread made of the substance, and moulding of many cornes. Wherunto Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> subscribing, thus <note place="margin">Aug in Psal. 98.</note> speaketh in the person of Christ: <hi>This body which you see you shall not eate, neither shall you drinke the bloud which they that crucifie mee shall shedde: I haue commended a Sacrament vnto you, which spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually vnderstoode shall quicken you.</hi> But to bee short, Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> (who setteth foorth fully and most effectually both the doctrine and right vse of the Lords Supper) is well worthie to decide this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, where diuers times in one piece of a Chapter after the wordes of consecration hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peates <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> the word, Bread. In conclusion therefore it must needes followe and bee graunted, striue the pieuish and peruerse Papistes neuer so much against it, that the name of the thing signified is giuen in this place to the signe it selfe: which is a figure, not straunge or newe;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18034:9"/> but vsuall and common, where mention is made of Sacraments: for, the Lorde, speaking of <hi>Circumcision,</hi> calleth it the Couenant: yet circumcision is not the <note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> couenant, but a signe of the couenant. And the <hi>Paschall Lambe</hi> is called the Lords Passeouer, though it was not the Passeouer, but the signe of the Passeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> &amp; serued onely to put men in remēbrance of that benefit; as it is afterward expounded: but leauing the holy scriptures, I will now proue the verie same point by the Authoritie of the holy Fathers. Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> in his booke of Questions vpon Leuiticus, hath these wordes: <hi>Solet res quae significat, eius rei nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quam significat, nuncupari.</hi> That is, The thing that <note place="margin">Aug. super Lev. quaest. 57.</note> doth signifie, is wont to bee called by the name of the thing that it doth signifie. And in the Epistle which hee wrote to <hi>Bonifacius: Si enim Sacramenta quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam similitudinem earum rerum, quarum Sacramenta</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ad Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facium. Epist. 13.</note>
               <hi>sunt, non haberent, omnino Sacramenta non essent: ex hac autem similitudine, plerunque etiam ipsarum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina accipiunt.</hi> If the Sacraments (saith he) had not some certaine similitude of the things whereof they be Sacraments, they should be no Sacraments: and of this similitude, many times they haue the names of those thinges themselues. Whereunto <hi>Theodore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. Dial. 1.</note> agreeth, and speaking of Christ thus subscribeth: <hi>Hee that did call his body wheate and bread, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a vine, doth honour the bread and wine with the name of his bodie, and bloud, not chaunging the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but adding grace vnto the Nature.</hi> And Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> hath the verie like wordes. Whereby <note place="margin">Chrysost. ad Caesarium.</note> it appeareth, and euen hereupon may rightly bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that the Romane transubstantiators haue no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18034:9"/> ground of reason, to affirme that there is more tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation in the Supper, by chaunge of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the signes, into the thing signified by the vertue of consecration, then in all the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For if there were such a change of substance, by the vertue of the Sacramentall wordes, and of the consecration of the signes, it should necessarily then come to passe, that the same should bee in all Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <note place="margin">Note well.</note> and not more in the one, then in the other; forsomuch as there is none at all that may bee Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments without consecration, and without Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall words, and they haue all this common toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the like reason is in them all, concerning this point. But to bee short, and yet for more full contentation, &amp; euen to giue satisfaction to the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest here present, that the signe is called by the name of the thing signified, and that there is no mutation in the substance of it, but onely in the vse; I do for further proofe in this behalfe, appeale to the outward senses: as, to the eyes, nose, mouth, taste, hands, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the reason of man, what it is, that wee doe receiue, when wee come at the feast of Easter, and at other times to the Lords Table. Whereunto in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering if these senses iumpe and agree, that it is bread and wine consecrated to a holy and heauenly vse; they verilie speake the truth and lye not: for there was neuer any transubstantiation and conuersion of one substance into another, but the outwarde senses iudged it to be so. As for example, when the rodde <note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> was turned into a Serpent, the Israelites sawe it: And when water was turned into wine at a Mariage, the guests saw it, and tasted it. But now in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Ioh. 2. 8.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18034:10"/> we do not see any such mutation: the bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sanctified taketh not the forme of flesh, neither doth the wine appeare to be bloud, but, as signes, do remaine all one in quantitie and qualitie, without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of substance. Whereby (beloued) albeit it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, as also by that which formerly hath beene deliuered, that our cōstruction concerning the words of the institution, is consonant &amp; right agreeable not onely to learning and religion, but to common sense also and reason: yet vtterly to ouerthrowe the false doctrine of popish transubstantiation, and to put it out of doubt, that we eate not Christs bodie carnally as our aduersaries dreame and grossely imagine, I wil now ouerturne by force of arguments and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reasons, the turning of the bread into the Body of Christ, and the wine into his bloud, though many as concerning this point (which yeelde from other points of superstition) do sticke, and are verie hard to be perswaded.</p>
            <p>That the substance of bread remaineth in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament <note place="margin">The first reasō against tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantion.</note> after the wordes of consecration, I will first proue it from the definition of a Sacrament. For the Fathers do affirme it to consist of an earthlie <note place="margin">August. Chrysost.</note> thing, and of an heauenly thing: of the Word, and of the Element. Now for the element and earthly thing to bee taken away by transubstantiation, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, and euen vtterly destroyeth, the verie nature of a Sacrament. And therefore from the definition thereof wee are well taught and instructed, that the bread, which is the element and earthly thing, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth still in substance without alteration, as well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as before the consecration; according to this say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18034:10"/> of Saint <hi>Augustine: The word commeth to the Element,</hi> (he sayth not taketh away the Element) <hi>and so it is made a Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, in Baptisme the substance of Water re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, <note place="margin">The second reason.</note> though it hath wordes of consecration, and is made a Sacrament of our Regeneration: and therefore in the Lords Supper, the bread and wine are not changed and done away vtterly: for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture speaketh as highly of the one as of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Againe, if the Elements of bread and wine <note place="margin">The third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note> are conuerted into the verie Bodie and Bloude of Christ: then the verie reprobates, as <hi>Iudas,</hi> should truely feede on the Bodie and Bloud of Christ, and so should bee saued: but this is false, and flat against the Scripture; <hi>Ergo,</hi> there is not any such conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
            <p>Againe, if the Papistes receiue Christs bodie in <note place="margin">The fourth reason.</note> the Sacrament, then they receiue either his mortall, or his immortall body. If they say, they receiue his mortall bodie: I might answere, that it cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte them; because mortall foode, is but for this mortall life: but I aunswere, that CHRIST hath not a mortall Bodie to communicate vnto them; for it is now chaunged, and hath putte on immortalitie. If they say, they receiue his immortall, and glorified Bodie, then like men slaine with their owne swordes, they must flie from this their text, <hi>Hoc est corpus meum;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause at the time when CHRIST spake these wordes to his Disciples hee had no glorified body: for the Sacrament was instituted before his death,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18034:11"/> and his body was not glorified vntill after his resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>Againe, if the Papistes receiue the verie same <note place="margin">The fift reason.</note> bodie of Christ in the sacrament, which he had from the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> and which was on the Crosse; thē it must haue the same naturall properties of a Body which that had, as proportion of shape, distinction of partes, extention of quantitie, circumscription of place, and the verie same substance of flesh, which he tooke of his Mother <hi>Marie:</hi> for these properties had Christes Body, that hung on the Crosse: but the bread (which they say, is turned into Christs Body) <note place="margin">Note here a great absurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> is without these and such like properties of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the bread is not turned really and substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially into the body of Christ which came from the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> and which was offered for vs on the Crosse.</p>
            <p>Againe, the breade in the Sacrament after the <note place="margin">The seauenth reason.</note> wordes of consecration is subiect to as many chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and chances as it was before: it may putrifie, and the wine may wax sharpe and turne into vinegar; yea, both of them may be mingled with ranke poyson: but the precious Body &amp; Bloud of Christ cānot be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with poyson; but is an excellent counterpoyson against all infection of sinne whatsoeuer: the Bodie of Christ cannot putrifie, the bloud of Christ can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not become sharpe or sowre as the outwarde signes may: the substance therefore of bread &amp; wine is not changed into the bodie and bloud of Christ, but remaineth still, after the wordes of consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Christ sitteth on the right hand of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The eight rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18034:11"/> (Hebrewes, 1.) <hi>and there shall remaine, touching his humanitie</hi> (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth) <hi>vntill the time that all thinges bee restored which God hath spoken by his Prophets,</hi> Acts, 3. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Christ is not bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in the Sacrament: for it is against the nature of a natural body to be in moe places then one at once. And therefore said Saint <hi>Augustine: Corpus domini in quo resurrexit, in vno loco esse oportet; veritas eius vbique diffusa est:</hi> the Bodie of Christ in the which he rose can be but in one place, though his trueth is dispersed euerie where.</p>
            <p>Againe, we are charged to do this in remēbrance <note place="margin">The ninth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. 1. Cor. 11.</note> of Christ; <hi>Do this</hi> (sayth hee) <hi>in remembrance of me,</hi> in remembrance of my benefit wrought for you, &amp; in remembrance of your saluation purchased by me. Now, remembrance is not of things present, but of thinges absent.</p>
            <p>Againe, it is recorded in the same Chapter, <hi>that</hi>
               <note place="margin">The tenth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note>
               <hi>whensoeuer wee eate the Lords Bread and drinke of his Cuppe, wee are sayde but to shewe his death vntill hee come:</hi> so that it is but a shewe and Representation of his Death, vntill his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p>Lastly (to omitte many other reasons) wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <note place="margin">The eleuenth reason.</note> that Christ shall come from heauen, and from no other place to iudge the quicke and the dead, and that in the same manner hee ascended: but if Christs Bodie bee made of breade, hee shall start out of the Pixe, and not come from heauen; yea, and that in <note place="margin">Note this wel.</note> another shape then when hee ascended. Which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish wonder, with other their strange deuises, so sauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of noueltie, that vnlesse our aduersaries haue still
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18034:12"/> whorish forheades they will blush and be ashamed: yea, and that the rather, in that against these and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such like arguments, and diuine reasons, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alledge any one testimonie of Scripture to proue their transubstantiation; but onely that Christ sayde, <hi>Hoc est corpus meum,</hi> This is my Body. Which words (as formerly appeareth) are not to bee vnderstoode properly, but figuratiuely: not naturally, but signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatiuely: not carnally, but spiritually. Yea, besides that which alreadie hath beene vttered, if the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auncient Fathers, in thus expounding them, make not with vs expressely, and against our said aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <note place="margin">The auncient Fathers affirme the wordes of Christ to be figuratiue.</note> directly, then the victorie shall bee theirs, and the shame and ouerthrowe ours: yea, then with the foole I will foolishly say, <hi>Non putâram. Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> being a holy Writer, and a verie auncient Father <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Contr. Marcion.</note> (for hee liued more then 1300. yeares since) expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them thus in his fourth booke against the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike <hi>Marcion: Acceptum panem, &amp; distributum dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulis, corpus suum illum fecit, dicendo, Hoc est corpus meum: id est, figura corporis mei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Christ taking the bread and distributing to his Disciples, made it his Body; saying, This is my Body: that is to say, this is a figure of my Bodie.</p>
            <p>And in his first booke against the same Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, the same Authour writeth after this manner: <note place="margin">Idem, lib. 1.</note>
               <hi>God did not reiect bread which is his creature; for by it he hath made a representation of his Bodie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> saith, <hi>The bread sanctified is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chrysost, ad Caesar.</note>
               <hi>counted worthie to bee called the Lords Body, etsi na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura panis in ipso permansit,</hi> though the nature of the bread remaine there still.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18034:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodoretus,</hi> aunswering to the obiection of an <note place="margin">Dialog. 2.</note> heretike, is right plaine in this point: for sayeth hee, <hi>Signa mystica post sanctificationem non recedunt a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura sua, sed manent in priori substantia, et figura, &amp; forma.</hi> That is, The mysticall tokens after the sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication depart not from their owne nature, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in their former substance, figure, and shape; yea, and are sensiblie seene to be the verie same they were before.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> speaking of Christ, sayth, <hi>He of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered not water but wine, for the figure of his bloud.</hi> Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi> sayeth, <hi>that the bread and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. de Sacra. lib. 4. cap. 4.</note>
               <hi>wine are the verie same they were, both in nature and substance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> hath written at large in many of his workes, and so plainely, against the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of transubstantiation, that our aduersaries the Papistes loue least to heare of him of all other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: partly for his authoritie, and partly because hee openeth the matter more fully then any other. For sayth hee, <hi>Christes flesh and bloud was in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. Contr. Faustū.</note>
               <hi>olde Testament promised by similitudes and signes of their sacrifices, and was exhibited indeed and in truth vpon the Crosse: but the same is now celebrated by a Sacrament of remembraunce vpon the Altar.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise against the heretike <hi>Adimantus,</hi> he thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: <note place="margin">Contr. Adim. lib. 4.</note>
               <hi>Non dubitauit dominus dicere, hoc est corpus meum, cùm signum daret corporis sui.</hi> Our Lorde doubted not (sayth he) to say, This is my body, when hee gaue a token of his Bodie. In an other place also, <hi>Christ tooke Iudas</hi> (sayth hee) <hi>vnto his Table,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in psal. 3.</note>
               <hi>wherat he gaue vnto his Disciples the figure of his body.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18034:13"/> Yea, and to this verie Sacrament hee applyeth this rule, <hi>Omnis res naturam et veritatem illarum rerum in se continet, ex quibus conficitur:</hi> that is, euerie thing keepeth and containeth the nature and truth of those things, of which it consisteth.</p>
            <p>Now (most Reuerēd, &amp; right blessed brethrē) if these &amp; other reuerend olde Fathers, writing to like effect, haue expounded the wordes of Christ rightly, then where is the papists transubstantiation?</p>
            <p>Surely, surely (deare Christians) how rightly and religiously they are by the Fathers expounded, it may wel be conceiued, in that not any one of the auncient writers euer spake of reall presence, or the literall sense of these words, <hi>This is my Body:</hi> yea, let our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries the Papists bring but one Catholick and godly learned Father, for the space of 700. years after Christ, that euer taught Popish transubstantiation, or that signified and insinuated any such matter; and we will not onely thereunto subscribe, but account also al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their vaine and vncatholike fancies, to bee right Catholike doctrine. But men, brethren, and Fathers, the best learned of that frowarde generation are so far from pleading either Canonicall Scriptures, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Fathers, as that either they say directly (as did <hi>Alphonsus</hi> a great Papist) <hi>that the auncient Fathers neuer knew transubstantiation;</hi> Or else doubtfully (as did <hi>Gabriel Biel,</hi> another popish doctor) <hi>that how the Body of Christ is in the Sacrament, it is not found ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vpon the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, lect. 40.</note>
               <hi>in the Canon of the Bible:</hi> Or else they say de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully (like craftie hucksters) that they must hold of the Sacraments as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth. Which third and last affirmation being fond and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18034:13"/> is vtterly to be contemned and condemned: for Transubstantiation was neuer heard of at <hi>Rome,</hi> or in any other part of the world, vntil it was there decreed in the late councell of <hi>Laterane,</hi> holden vnder Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third, in the yeare of our Lorde God <note place="margin">The age of the Papists new transubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is 393, yeares.</note> 1215. So that for the space of twelue hūdred &amp; fifteen years after Christ, the Church of God was well able to stand without it. Now therfore it stādeth vs in hand considering the newnesse of it, and that our Sauiour Christ in saying, <hi>This is my Bodie,</hi> did not abolish the substance of bread &amp; wine, but did vnite the force and fruit of his flesh crucified, and bloud shed for our sins, to the elements, that so receiuing the one, wee might through faith, and by the operation of his working spirit be partakers of the other; it stands vs (I say) in hand, not to bend our mindes on the outward signes of bread &amp; wine set before vs: but rather lifting vp our hearts from them to Christ, who liueth &amp; reigneth in heauen, it behoueth vs to behold him the very lambe of God slaine for the sins of the world, with the eyes and hands of our faith. <hi>Nam fide tangitur Christus, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de videtur: non corpore tangitur, non oculis comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur.</hi> For saith Saint <hi>Ambrose,</hi> By faith Christ is tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, <note place="margin">Ambr. in Luc. lib. 6.</note> by faith he is seene: hee is not touched with our bodie, nor viewed with our eyes. And elsewhere: <hi>Non corporali tactu Christum, sed fide tangimus.</hi> That is, we touch not Christ (sayth he) with our fingers, but with our faith.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> likewise crieth: <hi>To what end pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parest thou thy teeth and thy belly? beleeue, and thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. in Ioh. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ract. 25.</note>
               <hi>hast eaten.</hi> And in another place, <hi>We cannot</hi> (sayth he) <hi>handle Christ with our fingers: but with our faith wee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18034:14"/> may.</hi> Yea, that to beleeue in Christ is to eate his flesh and drinke his bloud, Christ himselfe thus proueth it: <hi>Hee that commeth to me shall not hunger; and he that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note>
               <hi>beleeueth in me, shall neuer thirst.</hi> By which faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, not we, vnder the Gospell onely, do eate Christs flesh and drinke his bloud; but the Patriarkes also, and Prophets, &amp; people of God which liued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the birth of Christ, did receiue him, and eate him, and liue by him: <hi>They did</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> auoucheth) <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note>
               <hi>all eate the same spirituall meat,</hi> that is to say, <hi>euen the same Christ that we eate, and did all drinke of the same spiritual drinke.</hi> Whosoeuer beleeued in Christ, they were nourished by him then, as we are now. They did not see Christ: he was not yet borne, he had not yet a naturall body, yet did they eate his body: he had not yet any bloud, yet did they drinke his bloud; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that it was he, in whom the promises shuld be fulfilled, they beleeued that hee should be that blessed seed in whom all Nations shold be blessed. Thus they beleeued, thus they receiued, and did eate his body. Wherupon, the premisses considered, it may rightly be inferred, that not our mouthes, but our minds; not our bellies, but our spirits, are nourished with the flesh &amp; bloud of Christ: &amp; that not by chewing, or swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; but by remembring and beleeuing that his body was wounded, &amp; his bloud shed for our perfect and eternall redemption.</p>
            <p>THus hauing hitherto declared (in handling the late doting deuise of transubstantiation; wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a manner dependeth all Poperie) and euen ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually proued by sufficient testimonies both out of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18034:14"/> the holy Scriptures, and holy auncient Fathers, that the nature of the bread remaineth in the Sacrament after the words of consecration, and that there is no mutation in substance, but in vse: it now further resteth but onely to point at an another horrible point of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish blasphemie, and so to committe you to God.</p>
            <p>Although (beloued) our Sauiour Christ comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Sacrament to bee ministred to all people in both kinds: yet our aduersaries the Papistes making euen him our Sauiour to haue no wit, nor vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what he did or said at his last supper, haue lately forbidden the mysticall Cuppe of his precious bloud to be ministred to the Laitie. Wherein how shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully soeuer, or rather how blasphemously these iollie fellowes, like iollie iuglers do iudge this matter: yet I am sure that the holy Scripture teacheth plainely, that the books of the auncient Writers testifie plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, and that continual practice for the space of a thousand yeares and vpwarde firmely pleadeth, and without contradiction, the contrarie. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the whole congregation, sayth: <hi>As often, as ye</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor 11. vers. 26. 27. 28.</note>
               <hi>shall eate this bread, and drinke this cuppe, yee shew the Lords death till hee come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, <hi>Whosoeuer</hi> (saith he) <hi>shal eat this bread, and drinke the cup of the Lord vnworthily, shall be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the bodie and bloud of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, <hi>Let euerie man</hi> (saith hee) <hi>examine himselfe, and so let him eate of this bread and drink of this cup.</hi> He doth not say, let the Pastor and Minister examine himselfe, &amp; so drinke of this cup; but euery man, euen euery Christiā. To iustifie which expositiō frō Christ himself by a generall affirmatiue, I appeal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18034:15"/> to the tenor of the institution. For as it was sayd, <hi>Take yee, eate yee:</hi> so it was said at the same time to the selfe same parties, <hi>Drinke ye all of this.</hi> Which two precepts <note place="margin">Arguments against halfe Communions.</note> Eate ye, drinke ye, compriseth all, both Laymen and Clerkes: and therefore both sorts are either to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, or else to be admitted to receiue in both kinds.</p>
            <p>Againe, the fruit &amp; effect of the bloud of Christ is common to the people with the Pastor: <hi>Ergo,</hi> being partners in the thing signified; the outward signe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which is the Communion of his bloud shed for the redemption of his people, ought to be diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently betweene them.</p>
            <p>Againe, A dead mans will may not bee changed: Nothing can be put to, nothing taken out, without <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 15.</note> forgerie and false-hood: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the cup of saluation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part of Christs will, &amp; testament, may not bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the Laitie without sacriledge &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy crueltie. And againe, if the water in Baptisme may not be taken away from the Lords people: then the cup of the new Testament may not be taken away frō them (for the bloud of Christ, whereby remission of sinnes is purchased, is represented by the wine of the Lords Supper, aswel as by the water in Baptisme): but the water in Baptisme may not be omitted or neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the cup of blessing may not (without great iniury done to the Lords people) be taken from them. Other arguments to this effect, &amp; in setting forth the truth hereo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I could vse many: but, knowing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this matter to bee such, as that the euidence &amp; clearnes of the thing it selfe speaketh for the proofe thereof, I am rather now disposed to call to witnesse in this behalfe the holy auncient Fathers.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18034:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> being a good olde Christian and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant <note place="margin">Note well the consent of the Fathers.</note> Martyr of Iesus Christ in the primitiue Church, writeth thus to the Church of <hi>Philadelphia: I exhort you, that you vse al one faith, one publique Ministerie &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ignat. ad Philad.</note>
               <hi>preaching of the word, and one Eucharist: for there is but one flesh of Iesus Christ, and one bloud shed for vs; one bread broken for all, and one cup distributed to all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> writing vnto <hi>Cornelius,</hi> saith, <hi>How do</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epist. 2.</note>
               <hi>we teach or prouoke them for the profession of his name to shed their bloud, if to them, going to the battail</hi> (spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Martyrs) <hi>wee shall denie his bloud? or how shall we make them fit for the cuppe of Martyrdome, if we admit them not first, by right of the communion, to the cup of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> saith, <hi>By the Sacrament of bread and of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 5. aduersus Marcionem.</note>
               <hi>the cuppe, we haue proued in the Gospell the veritie of the bodie &amp; of the bloud of our Lord, against the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasticall dreames of</hi> Marcion.</p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> administring the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note place="margin">Chrysost. in 2. ad Cor. Hom. 18.</note> himselfe in the famous Citie of <hi>Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> is so plaine in this point, that nothing can be plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: for (saith he) <hi>There is a thing wherein the Priest differeth nothing from the people; as when he must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the dreadfull Mysteries. For it is not here, as it was in the olde Law, where the Priest eate one part aad the people another, neither was it lawfull for the people to be partaker of those things which the Priest was: but now it is not so, but rather one body is proposed to al &amp; one cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, to the end that all men may see and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what great iniurie is done to Christian people (for whom Christ died) by Pope-catholikes, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18034:16"/> Heretikes, especially that such false Catholikes themselues may cōfesse it, if not with their mouthes, at the least in their consciences; I will call at this time two Popes to witnesse. Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the first, in whose dayes the communion vnder both kindes was so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie and certaine, as that it was the marke whereby to knowe the Manachees, the most pernicious Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes that were in the Church, thus auoucheth: <hi>They take in their vnworthie mouthes the Body of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. quadrag. 4.</note>
               <hi>and refuse altogether to drinke the bloud of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption;</hi> which he calleth a sacrilegious hypocrisie. And Pope <hi>Gelasius</hi> speaking not of the Manachees, <note place="margin">De consecra. distinct. 2. cap.</note> as <hi>Leo</hi> doth, but of other persons receiued into the Christian Church, thus vttereth his iudgement; <hi>Wee haue heard, that some hauing onely receiued the holie portion of the bodie, do abstaine from the cuppe of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">If Popes tell you this tale take heede ye Papists to your consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</note>
               <hi>holie bloud: but sith that they are mooued by a fond superstition, which I know not, thus to abstaine, either let them receiue the whole Sacrament, or els let them be wholly and vtterly restrained and shutte out from the same: for there can bee no diuision of this one Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and highe mysterie, without great Sacriledge.</hi> Whereby it appeareth, euen in the iudgement of these Popes, that if we will not incur &amp; run into ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, violent, and wilfull Sacriledge, the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion must bee ministred to all men, without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in both kindes, according to the right intention of Christ Iesus, and according to that course which the Christian world diligently obserued for the space of 1230. yeares, and euer after also (but euen in some few places onely) vntill in the late Councell of <hi>Constance</hi> a wicked decree and vngodly was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18034:16"/> made to the contrarie. Whereupon, <hi>Gerson</hi> a great Papist being a chiefe agent in that Councell, with other the Popes Proctours and Doctours of speciall reputation, did so beate their braines to iustifie that Acte in that Councell established, as that they almost lost their foreheades. For the considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by them alleadged, wherewith they were ledde thus to chaunge the last Will and Testament of CHRIST IESVS, are but verie poore shiftes and most miserable inducementes: as, the length of Lavmens beardes, the costlinesse of wine; the difficulties first of getting, then of keeping wine from sowring, from freezing, and breedinge of flies. All which and many such like foolish and friuolous toyes thus hatched by their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, being no lesse ridiculous then the fact was impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, must stand for reason (if wee will bee ruled by a whorish Mother the Church of Antichrist) against all reason and religion.</p>
            <p>Now what is mockerie, or what is iniurie to GOD and man, if it bee religion and pietie, in respect of long beards, in respect of frostes in winter, and flies in Summer, to correct Christs institution, and to chase the Lay people from the cuppe of their saluation, from the Communion of Christs bloud, and fellowshippe of his holy spirite? Surely, surely (beloued) howsoeuer these daintie Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines haue lately thus fallen into great blindnesse, or rather wilfull madnesse: yet vndoubtedly no Church euer resisted mangled Communions with greater ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemēcie thā the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did, til couetousnes &amp; pride blinded her eies, &amp; hardned her heart against
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18034:17"/> God and his sonne Christ: Which God for Christ his sake open the eyes of her corrupt Children, and so mollifie their hearts, as that they may receiue Christs holy Mysteries, not according to their owne fond fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; doting dreames; but according to the first insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution thereof, &amp; according to the general practice of all Christian Churches in former times. For otherwise if they still lead their dayes in voluntarie blindnesse, &amp; wilfull wickednesse, they shall die in their sinnes: ye<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, death and damnation shall be their portion for euer: because they haue pleasure in their owne inuentions, and do not giue their hearts to receiue to beleeue, &amp; to loue the truth. From which death and damnation, hee deliuer both them and vs, who to receiue the blessed Sacrament in both kindes by his last wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs, euen Iesus Christ the righteous: to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghost, three persons in Trinitie, one eternall, euer liuing, and euerlasting God in vnitie, be rendered all power, all praise, all might, and all maiestie, both now, and for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18034:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>